all right everybody welcome back
in today's lesson here we are going to
be talking about how we approach a very
important question when it comes to
our patients are they fluid responders
does our patient need fluids or do they
need something else
we find that about 50 of our patients
respond to fluid
while the other half just don't since
there are some very serious consequences
to using fluid and the critically ill
there has to be some way to determine
who is going to respond
with better odds than just a coin flip
in this lesson here i'm going to dive
into some of the strategies that we have
to evaluate our patients fluid
responsiveness
[Music]
all right you guys and welcome back to
another video lesson from icu advantage
my name is eddie watson and my goal with
this channel is to try to give you the
confidence to succeed in the icu
by taking these complex critical care
subjects and making them easy to
understand
i hope that i'm able to do just that for
you guys and if i am i invite you to
subscribe to the channel below
when you do make sure you hit that bell
icon and select all notifications so you
never miss out when i release a new
lesson
and then when you're done with the
lesson make sure you head on over to
icuadvantage.com or follow the link down
the lesson description
to take the quiz on this lesson here and
be entered into our weekly drawings for
gift cards
all right so with that out of the way
the great question of whether or not our
patients need fluid
is really one of the great challenges
that has existed since the dawn of
critical care management
fluids for patients who need them can be
a very important tool in helping to
optimize our patient
but for others can have very real
consequences that will not only work
against us but can also increase length
of stay
and mortality and so for these reasons
we need to have a way to try and
determine
as best as we possibly can whether our
patient will actually need fluids
or whether we need to try some other
approaches and the fact of the matter is
that some just don't now in order to
better understand the why behind the use
of fluids
we really need to understand what we
hope to achieve by actually giving them
fluids
and so let's talk about that why do we
give fluids
so with our patients in the multitude of
different
icus and different physiological
processes that they have going on
there can really be a wide variety of
reasons that are contributing to the
need of fluids
our patients could be bleeding and
hypovolemic they could be dehydrated and
hypovalemic
they could be septic and having a
relative hypovolemia
very different processes but the same
end result
that the volume of blood returning to
the heart aka our preload
is not enough to support an adequate
cardiac output
and thus an adequate perfusion and so in
order to better understand
why this is we need to bring up
everyone's favorite friend
the frank starling law and really the
frank starling curve
now while i'm not going to go into
detail about it here you need to
understand the basics of what this all
means to your patient
and the essence of what they described
was that the length of the myocardial
tissue
is directly related to the force of the
subsequent contraction
the more we stretch the muscle fibers
the stronger they're going to contract
and what stretches these fibers is what
we refer to as our preload
so when we look at the graph of the
curve
we have preload on the bottom and stroke
volume
on the left hand side and then here we
have an example of a curve of
a normal patient the key takeaway here
is that on the left side of this curve
if we increase our preload we also see
an
increase in their stroke volume these
are actually patients who we consider to
be
preload dependent now as we move further
to the right
we begin to see the curve flatten and
increases in preload are really met with
less and less of an increase in stroke
volume until we either see
no change and then even some decrease if
we go further
these are the patients who are preload
independent
and what this all means is that our
patient who is preload dependent will
see a benefit to their stroke volume if
we give them fluid
and the patient who is preload
independent will not now
important to know too is that the shape
and position of the curve
will vary between individuals so here we
have an
example of a hyperdynamic patient
here would be a hypodynamic patient and
then down here would be an example of
someone in cardiogenic shock
as you can see depending on what's going
on with our patient and how their
particular curve
is we're going to find very different
responses to
various different amounts of preload and
or changes in that preload
now this is very simplistic but this is
the core
of what we need to understand to try and
determine if our patients need fluid or
not
if we will not see an increase in their
stroke volume thus their cardiac output
we really shouldn't be giving them fluid
so now that we understand what we're
trying to do with fluids we're left with
the age-old question
how do we know if they need fluids how
do we know
where on the frank starling curve they
reside
and then remember that our patient does
not present at one point on the curve
and stay there
as things change with them so does the
dynamic of whether or not they're going
to respond to fluid
and so over time we've developed
different assessments
and measures to try and determine our
patient's fluid responsiveness
and really the first of these that i
want to talk about are going to be our
clinical indications
at the heart of anything we do we need
to always take in the information that
is readily available to us
the most basic but sometimes
underestimated of these is going to be
that look
listen feel approach of our assessment
there is a lot of information that's at
our disposal here that can be indicators
that our patient may need fluid
the first of these indicators is going
to be our patient's heart rate
now here an elevated heart rate may be a
sign of compensation
in the presence of hypovolemia and
decreased perfusion
with our patient's blood pressure a
decreasing blood pressure especially in
the presence of that elevated heart rate
can again be a sign that the
compensation mechanism is
not enough to really sustain the
perfusion we can also look at our
patient's respiratory rate sustained
hypoperfusion can really lead to rising
lactate and metabolic acidosis
to which the body may increase the
respiratory rate to try and blow off co2
and compensate for this acidosis
we can also keep an eye on our patient's
urine output a decrease in the urine
output to less than one milligram per
kilogram per hour
may be a sign that your patient is in
need of fluids now we do also have some
assessment findings that may also alert
us to the possibility of needing fluids
these would be things like decreased
capillary refill
weakened peripheral pulses cool clammy
skin
and dry mucous membranes and then
finally we can look at some of our lab
findings like
elevated bun and creatinine
transaminitis
elevated lactic acid and then
hemoconcentration with an elevated
hematocrit
now while each of these alone may not
tell us if our patient needs fluid
you do want to look at the collection of
information as a whole
as well as really considering what is
going on with our patient and this is
going to help to guide our thinking of
whether or not they would respond to
fluid
and so this kind of leads into talking
about some of our static versus dynamic
measures
so after taking in all the clinical
indications we can also assess other
information that may be at our disposal
to try and determine
where they might be on that frank
starling curve when we talk about these
other measures
we can think of them as either being
static or dynamic
now static measures are a single
perspective on what is going on
one pressure one reading much of our
clinical indications that i just talked
about are actually static measures
they only give us information at a
moment in time and are only looking at a
single factor
now our dynamic measures on the other
hand will look at the relationship
between two factors
the heart and the lungs and this will
make much more sense in a minute as i
talk about
our different dynamic measurements so
the first of these measures that i want
to talk about is actually going to be
our central venous pressure or
cvp so this which we obtain from either
a central line or a swan
is still one of the most widely used
indicators for preload and in fact
studies have found that a third of
providers are using this measure
and in many cases this may be one of our
only indicator measures that we have
available to us
and the thought here is that cvp
directly relates to our patient's
preload
and so what this should really tell us
is that the lower the cvp
the more responsive someone should be to
fluid
and the higher the less responsive so if
i drew that out on a graph here and we
looked at our
cvp and our patient's fluid
responsiveness
as we begin increasing the cvp we should
see the patients become
less responsive to fluid and in healthy
individuals we actually find this to be
true
the problem that we find is that when
dealing with critically ill patients
when they looked at the data and really
plotted the cvp and whether the patients
responded to fluid
this is actually what we found cvp would
seem to have no real correlation with
whether a patient is fluid responsive
and so cvp is actually something that we
consider to be a static measure it does
not take into account other factors that
can also be working either for
or against our ability to stretch that
myocardial tissue
for any given cvp it's simply a measure
of
pressure a moment in time and doesn't
take in these other
factors so for example an older
gentleman
who has a non-compliant stiff ventricle
may have a quote-unquote high
cvp and be normal and still fluid
responsive
a younger person with a compliant
ventricle could have the same cvp
and be off on the fluid independent part
of the curve
the number itself doesn't tell us
anything
now from here we can talk about our
pulmonary artery occlusive pressure or
pulmonary capillary reg pressure
whatever you want to call it
here we're using a swan to get the
pressure inside of the pulmonary artery
and we use this as a surrogate for
left-sided preload now as you can
probably figure out once again
we face some of the same challenges when
we're using this static parameter
and it doesn't take into account other
things that could impact what this
pressure is
and so just like with the cbp in these
critically ill
patients we tend to find that there's
really no correlation
between this number and whether a
patient is fluid responsive
and so that leads me into talk about a
couple other measures that we have
and these are ones that we actually
classify as dynamic measures
and again for the dynamic measure we're
looking at the relationship
between the heart and the lungs so
what's happening here is that as the
lungs expand
they increase our intrathoracic pressure
this increase in intrathoracic pressure
is going to reduce venous return to the
heart
decreasing our preload it also puts
pressure on the heart and decreases its
filling volume as well
as a result with inflated lungs we see
decreases in stroke volume now as the
lungs deflate we see the intrathoracic
pressure go down
increasing preload and then thus
increasing stroke volume
and so this expansion deflation
inspiration
expiration leads to cyclical changes in
our patient stroke volume which we can
actually measure
when a patient is fluid dependent we see
greater variation
and thus we find these dynamic measures
to actually be better indicators of
fluid responsiveness
and these two different measures are
something we refer to as
pulse pressure variation or ppv and
stroke volume variation
or svv now ppv and svv
are just two different measures of
essentially the same thing
and so let's start off talking about our
pulse pressure variation
so here when we look at this pulse
pressure this is going to be the
difference from the
end diastolic pressure to the peak
systolic pressure
and so here's an example of an arterial
tracing
and you can definitely see that
variation in fact i'm sure you guys have
probably seen this before on the monitor
and what we can do is we can actually
measure these points in these values and
we're going to compare the pulse
pressure from the highest point that we
see here which is going to be at the end
of expiration
to the lowest point down here which is
going to be the end of
inspiration when we compare those two
pulse pressures we can see the
difference between them
if we find this difference to be greater
than or equal to 13 percent
this patient is going to be fluid
responsive now when we look at our
stroke volume variation
that this actually requires special
equipment something like the vigilaio
or the flow track and it has to be able
to calculate the area
underneath the arterial tracing as you
see here
up until the aortic valve closes at the
aortic notch
now here then what we're going to do is
we're going to compare this volume
again at the highest point end of
expiration to the lowest point end of
inspiration
and then see what kind of variance we
have if it's greater than or equal to 13
again once again these patients are
going to be fluid responsive
now as i said these dynamic measures we
actually
found to be good indicators of fluid
responsiveness in our patients
but unfortunately we do have some
limitations with them they really only
hold true as a measure of fluid
responsiveness in certain situations
first our patients have to be
mechanically ventilated on positive
pressure ventilation
they also have to be synchronous with
that ventilation we actually have to be
giving them eight milliliters per
kilogram for their volumes
and they have to have moderate amount of
peeps so less than 10.
in addition to that they also have to
have a regular rhythm they have to have
normal intra-abdominal pressure as well
as normal thoracic compliance
if all of this isn't true then we really
can't rely on these measures
to be good indicators of whether our
patients are fluid responsive
and so our patient who is awake and
spontaneously breathing
this is going to be of no value to us
now another possible way to get some
measures is going to be with the use of
bedside ultrasound
now we've actually seen a growth in the
use of bedside ultrasound to help
evaluate the critically ill patient
and it's great because this is a
non-invasive tool with a lower risk
profile especially when comparing it
against something like the insertion of
a swan
and there's actually a lot that can be
determined with ultrasound but when it
comes to fluid responsiveness there are
a few main things that we're looking for
now keep in mind this is going to be a
very quick overview of these here
but one of the things that we look for
is our ivc diameter and its
collapsibility
now this though is actually correlated
with right atrial pressure or cvp
thus this is just another static measure
we can also look at the ivc
distensibility index
this is going to be a dynamic measure of
the change in size of the ivc
with respirations on a mechanically
intubated patient
and so again we're going to see some of
the same limitations that we see with
our pulse pressure variation and our
stroke volume variation
we can also look at our sub aortic pulse
velocity and here we're comparing the
velocity
of variation of blood being ejected into
the aorta
and once again this is another dynamic
measure and still has those same
limitations with our ppv or
svv there's another test we can do which
is the end expiratory occlusive test
and so here we're going to do an end
expiratory pause maneuver and we're
going to check for variability
in the ivc diameter with respiration now
once again this is another dynamic
measure and has its limitations but
these limitations are actually less than
with
our ppv or svv and we can use this with
patients who are doing some spontaneous
breathing
with the ultrasound we can also
determine our patient's stroke volume
this is a calculation that uses the
velocity time integral
as well as the lvot size and this can be
used to
evaluate as well as determine changes in
our patient's stroke volume
so again with the ultrasound like other
measures there are potential
issues in being able to truly determine
our patient's fluid volume status
and really we should treat this as once
again another quiver
in our tool kit for evaluating all the
information that we have on what's going
on
all right so we've covered many
different measures of possible
indicators of fluid responsiveness both
from static to dynamic measures
now while the dynamic measures do offer
greater indication
of the true volume status of our patient
just like with static measures they do
have their limitations in some
situations now given the complexities
and limitations it is important that we
take all this information together
in the context of what's going on with
our patient and try and best determine
what their fluid volume status is
this really isn't an exact science we
don't have any
foolproof way to say 100 that this
patient is going to be
fluid responsive and so that really
leads us to ask
is there even a way to truly dynamically
determine for any patient
especially the awake patient if they
would benefit from fluids
and so here enter our passive leg raise
or plr
so the beauty of the passive leg raise
is that this technique can work
on both our awake and our intubated
patients
and is really pretty simple to perform
so the way this works is we start with
the patient sitting up at 45 degrees
and we do need to have a way to measure
their stroke volume
or their cardiac output and so this can
be done with a swan or a pa cath
even something like a vigilaio or a flow
track if we want
a less invasive measure and we can also
use the bedside ultrasound like i talked
about for a non-evasive way to measure
the stroke volume
and so after we have that measure we are
going to lay the patient flat and then
we're going to
raise their legs to 45 degrees and so
what we're doing here
is we're redistributing the venous
return from the lower legs to the
central circulation
and this is effectively giving them a
transient fluid bolus without actually
giving them any fluid and this is the
equivalent to
around 500 ml of a fluid bolus we then
monitor their stroke volume and or their
cardiac
index it usually takes at least 30 to 90
seconds to see the maximum
effect and if we see an increase of at
least 10 percent
in their stroke volume or 15 in their
cardiac index
that this indicates a high probability
that they will be fluid responsive
now the fluid bolus that we're giving
them is actually temporary and
as soon as we reposition them back to
normal this is going to go away
and what's really great about this is we
can repeatedly use this technique
to continue to evaluate their
responsiveness and then finally there
are some patients that just may not be
able to do the passive leg raise
in cases with these patients we can also
do a small
fluid bolus typically anywhere from 100
to 250 ml
to serve as a fluid challenge so here
again we want to be able to measure
stroke volume or cardiac index take
record of that measurement before giving
the fluid
and then again after we give them the
bolus and it's infused here again if we
see the same 10
stroke volume or 15 cardiac index that
once again this is going to potentially
indicate that they
are a fluid responder so that's sort of
our approach and evaluation when it
comes to whether or not
our patient is going to be responsive to
giving them fluids or not
it's really important that we have some
way of determining
where our patient lies on this frank
starling curve
because we don't want to be giving them
fluids if we don't have to but we also
want to determine those patients who
would benefit from it
so i covered a lot of information here
but hopefully this helps to give you
guys a little bit better of an idea
of some of the measures and assessments
and tools that we have at our disposal
to try and determine who these patients
are
i hope that you guys were able to learn
something from this and that you guys
liked the lesson
if you did please leave me a like down
below it really goes a long way to help
support this channel in the eyes of the
youtube algorithm
also leave me a comment down below let
me know what you thought of this lesson
i love reading your comments and trying
to respond to every one of you guys
as well as subscribe to the channel if
you haven't already make sure and share
this lesson with anybody else too that
you think might find it useful
a special shout out to the awesome
youtube and patreon members out there
the support that you guys are willing to
show this channel is truly appreciated
and is really going to allow me to
continue to grow and do better things
with this channel in the future
for the rest of you guys if you'd be
interested in showing support for this
channel and seeing some of the
additional perks that you get for doing
just that
you can join the youtube membership down
below or head on over to the patreon
page and check out what those benefits
are
you can also support this channel by
following some of the links down in the
lesson description
as well as checking out some of the
awesome shirt designs i have down there
as well
make sure you stay tuned for the next
lesson in the series otherwise check out
a couple awesome lessons i'm gonna link
to right here
as always thank you guys so much for
watching have a great day